Guide to the Montana Legislative Assembly (25th: 1937) records 1936-1937
Montana Historical Society
Montana Legislative Assembly (25th: 1937) records
1936-1937
Montana Historical Society Archives
LR 25
Montana. Legislative Assembly.
1.2 linear feet of shelf space
This collection contains the records of the Montana 25th (1937) Legislative Assembly including the minutes of the House Special Committees; minutes of the Senate Select Committees; House and Senate bills, memorials, resolutions, and status reports; and Joint memorials and resolutions. [Maps and printed material transferred to Library; OVERSIZE MATERIAL: Map case]
The Montana State Legislature is made up of two chambers, the Senate and the House of Representatives. The Constitution of Montana limits the size of the Senate to no fewer than 40 and no more than 50 members and the size of the House of Representatives to no fewer than 80 and no more than 100 members. Each house is responsible for choosing its officers, creating committees and establishing its own rules. The Montana Legislature meets for 90 days every odd numbered year, beginning the first Monday in January, or the following Wednesday if the first Monday is New Years Day. The first State Legislature convened on November 23, 1889, fifteen days after Montana became a state. Each following Legislature has been numbered sequentially.
The 25th Montana Legislature met from January 4th to March 4th, 1937. The leaders of the Senate were Hugh Adair (D-President), Leonard Plank (D-President Pro Tempore), and Harry Meyer (D-Majority Leader). The leaders of the House were H.D. Rolph (D-Speaker), George Monahan (D-Speaker Pro Tempore), and Sam Spiegel (D-Majority Leader).
Sources:The Constitution of the State of Montana as adopted by the Constitutional Convention March 22, 1972, and as ratified by the people, June 6, 1972, referendum no. 68, "A GUIDE TO THE MONTANA LEGISLATURE," The Montana Legislature,; “Montana Legislative Leadership 1889 – Present”.
The collection mainly consists of minutes of the House Special Committees to Investigate the State Auditor and Commissioner of Insurance and the Silver Bow County Elections; reports, testimonies, and subpoenas from the Senate Select Committee to Investigate the State Board of Equalization; and minutes, reports, financial records, and correspondence from Select Committee to investigate the State Highway Commission. Also included in the collection are House and Senate bills, memorials, resolutions, and status reports; and Joint memorials and resolutions (re Senator J.D. Garber). [Maps and printed material transferred to Library; OVERSIZE MATERIAL: Map case]
The collection is organized into three series, House of Representatives, Senate, and Miscellany.
The series House of Representatives is organized into seven subseries, Special Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically), House Bills (arranged numerically), House Resolutions (arranged numerically), House Joint Resolutions (arranged numerically), House Statue Reports (arranged chronologically), House Memorials(arranged numerically), and House Joint Memorials (arranged numerically).
The series Senate is organized into nine subseries, Senate Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically), Senate Bills (arranged numerically), Senate Special Committee Reports (arranged alphabetically), Senate Resolutions (arranged numerically), Senate Joint Resolutions (arranged numerically), Senate Status Reports (arranged chronologically), Senate Memorials (arranged numerically), Senate Joint Memorials (arranged numerically), and Senate Memorial Resolutions (arranged alphabetically).
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request.
Maps and printed material transferred to Library; OVERSIZE MATERIAL: Map case
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Bills, Legislative--Montana.; Legislative bodies--Montana--Committees.; Political corruption.
Montana--Politics and government.; Silver Bow County (Mont.)--Politics and government.
Montana.; Government and Politics.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- House of Representatives
  - House Special Committee Minutes
    - Special Committee to Investigate the Methods and Practices of the State Auditor and the Ex-Officio Commissioner of Insurance to Determine the Standing and Report the Administration of the State Insurance Law, and the Handling of Policies under Such Act, and of the State Board of Examiners as to the Insurance on State Property and to Investigate the Reinsurance Contract (responses from insurance companies to the committee's request for information; includes report by committee), 1937 February (Box-folder 1 / 1)
    - Special Committee to Investigate Silver Bow County Elections ("Record and Transcript of Testimony," Vols. I-III; index included with vol. II), 1937 February 14-1937 March 4 (Box-folder 1 / 2-4)
  - House Bills
    - Bill Nos. 1, 3-4, 6-9, 11-13, 15, 17-20, 22, 26-27, 29-30, 32-33, 36-40, 42, 44, 47-49, 51, 53, 55-56, 58-60, 63-67, 72-75, 77-86, 88-89, 91, 94-98 (also Substitute for House bill nos. 10, 14, 28, 31, 47), 1937 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
    - Bill Nos. 100, 102, 104, 108-109, 111-117, 119-124, 126-135, 137-138, 140-146, 148-151, 153-154, 157-172, 174, 176-177, 179-183, 185, 187-189, 192-199, 200-205, 207, 209-216, 218-219, 221-222, 225-235, 238, 240-246, 248, 250, 252, 254-256, 260, 262-268, 270-271, 274, 276, 279, 282-289, 292-292, 296 (partial), 298, 300-301, 303, 305, 309-310, 312-327, 329-333, 337-338, 340, 343-344, 347, 349-350, 352, 354, 357-358, 360-366, 369-372, 374-377, 379-381, 384, 391-392, 394-396, 399, 403-405, 409-418 (also Substitute for House bill nos. 107, 120, 155-156, 339, 341; Senate Substitute for House bill no. 154), 1937 (Box-folder 2 / 1-4)
  - House Resolutions
    - Bill No. 2, 1937 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
  - House Joint Resolutions
    - Bill Nos. 1-6, 1937 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
  - House Status Reports
    - 11th, 12th, 16th-33rd, 37th-46th, 49th, 56th, 60th, Legislative Days, 1937 (Box-folder 2 / 6a)
  - House Memorials
    - Bill nos. 1, 3-4, 1937 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - House Joint Memorials
    - Bill nos. 1-11, 13, 1937 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
- Senate
  - Senate Standing Committee Minutes
    - Senate Judiciary Committee, 1937 January 11-March 4 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
  - Senate Bills
    - Bill nos. 1-3, 5-9, 11-12, 14-16, 18-22, 24-28, 30-34, 36-46, 48-50, 52-54, 56-61, 64-65, 67, 70-72, 74-76, 78-80, 82-99, 100-101, 103-104, 107, 110, 112-113, 115-130, 132-133, 135-141, 143-148, 150-157, 160-162, 164-165, 171-172, 174-178, 180, 182-195 (also Substitute Senate bills nos. 3-4, 55, 81, 90; for Senate Substitute for House Bill no. 154, see House Bills), 1937 (Box-folder 2 / 10-11)
  - Senate Special Committee Reports
    - Select Committee to Investigate the State Board of Equalization, 1937 (Box-folder 2 / 12)
    - Committee to Investigate the State Highway Commission (Minutes; includes notes), 1937 January 19-30 (Box-folder 2 / 13-14)
    - Committee to Investigate the State Highway Commission (Minutes), 1937 February 2-11 (Box-folder 3 / 1-3)
    - Committee to Investigate the State Highway Commission (Correspondence), 1936 January-1937 February, undated (Box-folder 3 / 4)
    - Committee to Investigate the State Highway Commission (Exhibits nos. 7-8, 10-12, 14-18, 29-30), 1937 (Box-folder 3 / 5)
    - Committee to Investigate the State Highway Commission (Exhibits A-C), 1937 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
    - Committee to Investigate the State Highway Commission (Financial records), 1937 (Box-folder 3 / 7)
    - Committee to Investigate the State Highway Commission (Legislation), 1937 (Box-folder 3 / 8)
    - Committee to Investigate the State Highway Commission (Memoranda), 1937 (Box-folder 3 / 9)
    - Committee to Investigate the State Highway Commission (Miscellaneous, includes questions of witness; status of highway financial districts as of January 1937; portion of Rockwood Brown testimony; etc.) (Box-folder 3 / 10)
    - Committee to Investigate the State Highway Commission (Report), 1937 (Box-folder 3 / 11)
    - Committee to Investigate the State Highway Commission (State Resolutions to Appoint Investigate Committee), 1937 (Box-folder 3 / 12)
    - Committee to Investigate the State Highway Commission (Subpoenas), 1937 (Box-folder 3 / 13)
  - Senate Resolutions
    - Bill nos. 2, 3, 5, 8, 1937 (Box-folder 3 / 14)
  - Senate Joint Resolutions
    - Bill nos. 1-3, 5-6, 8-9, 1937 (Box-folder 3 / 15)
  - Senate Status Reports
    - 33rd, 35th, 41st, 48th, 51st-55th, 58th, 60th Legislative Day, 1937 (Box-folder 3 / 15a)
  - Senate Memorials
    - Bill nos. 6, 7, 1937 (Box-folder 3 / 16)
  - Senate Joint Memorials
    - Bill nos. 3-10, 1937 (Box-folder 3 / 17)
  - Senate Memorial Resolutions
    - re Senator J.D. Garber, 1937 January 7 (Box-folder 3 / 18)
- Miscellany
  - Lists of maps and printed materials transferred to the Library Map Collection and to the Library respectively, 1937 (Box-folder 3 / 19)
  - Committee Announcements, 1937 (Box-folder 3 / 20)
  - Seating Chart, House of Representatives [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: Map case], 1937 (Box-folder 3 / OVFD)
  - "Yearly Salaries and Positions of Employees of Units of University of Montana," 1936; "Yearly Salaries and Positions of Employees of the Custodial Institutions," 1936; "Yearly Salaries and Positions of Employees of State Departments", 1937 (Box-folder 3 / 21)